A Guide to the Dorothy Lee Baugher Papers, 1936-2003 (bulk 1975-1981)
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
Dorothy Lee Baugher Papers 1936-2003 (bulk 1975-1981)
Special Collections, James Madison University
3017
1.25 hollinger boxes; .52 linear feet
The Dorothy Lee Baugher Papers, 1936-2003, consists of 1.25 Hollinger boxes of newspaper clippings, poetry, fiction and non-fictin writings, and drawings produced by Baugher. The collection also includes miscellaneous materials including correspondence, receipts, programs, and notes.
Dorothy Lee Baugher
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Purchased by a private donor at an estate auction in November 2008 and subsequently donated to Special Collections in July 2009.
Biographical Information
Dorothy Lee Baugher (1917-2009) graduated from Madison College in 1939. While a student, she served as a member of the art staff for the Schoolma'am yearbook. A McGaheysville native, Baugher taught art and English at Turner Ashby High School and in 1975 became the editor for the "Footprints and echoes" column for the Bicentennial at the the Daily News-Record. Baugher's interests included art, pottery, writing fiction and non-fiction, and poetry.
Scope and Content
The Dorothy Lee Baugher Papers, 1936-2003, is arranged in five series and consists of 1.25 hollinger boxes of newspaper clippings, poetry, fiction and non-fiction writtings, and drawings produced by Baugher. The collection also includes miscellaneous materials including correspondence, receipts, programs, and notes.
Series I, Daily News-Record Materials, 1975-1981, is comprised of newspaper clippings written by Baugher on subjects pertaining to the United States Bicentennial (1976) as well as the city of Harrisonburg's Bicentennial (1980) in the "Footprints and Echoes" column of the Daily News-Record. Topics range from Revolutionary War efforts in the Valley, women's roles in the Revolution, and general daily life in the late 18th century. The series includes some of Baugher's typed drafts as well as her drawings, many of which were sketched on the backs of cereal and food boxes. The sketches were published alongside her articles in the Daily News-Record. An index of these writings is available here.
Series II, Non-Fiction, n.d., includes a variety of short stories and essays of historical and religious content. Baugher's writings reference Patrick Henry, Stonewall Jackson, Pendleton Bryan, and the Methodist Church. The non-fiction works also include narrative Bible stories about Christmas, Zachariah and Elizabeth, and Thomas the Apostle or Didymus.
Series III, Fiction, 2002-2003, n.d., is comprised of notes, drafts, manuscripts, and short stories. Included in this series is a children's story entitled "Corky" about a pig which was also illustrated by Baugher. Written under the pseudonym Dorothy Lee Desailles, "The Reluctant Heart" is Baugher's most extensive work. This unpublished full-length manuscript is set dually in the Caribbean and the United States with religious connotations, a variety of characters, a love-angle, and mystery. Numerous drafts of "The Reluctant Heart" are retained. Ficticious short stories, notes, and resource material for potential works or works in progress are also present.
Series IV, Poetry, 1986-1998, n.d., is a collection of handwritten and typed poems written by Baugher. Much of the poetry has religious themes with references to God and Bible verses. Notes on potential publishing companies are also present.
Series V, Miscellany, 1936-2003, consists of various church and community programs, correspondence, notes, and other ephemera. Specific materials include J.C. Penney employee's sales receipts, the Turner Ashby Class of 1961 "Progress Report" (1981 ed.) in which class members describe their lives and families twenty years after graduating, and a Daily News-Record article and Op-Ed piece recognizing Baugher for her work in the community.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series:
I. Daily News-Record Materials, 1975-1981
II. Non-Fiction, n.d.
III. Fiction, 2002-2003, n.d.
IV. Poetry, 1986-1998, n.d.
V. Miscellany, 1936-2003
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Daily News-Record, August 15, 2009
Schoolma'am, 1939.
AN 93-0916 Commencement programs, 1910-present; June 5, 1939 program.
Related Material/Collections
For similar collections pertaining to JMU alumni, see the JMU Historical Collection.
Contents List
- Daily News-Record Materials, 1975-1981
  - Manuscripts (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - June 1975-December 1979 (Box-folder 1:2)
    - January 1980-n.d. (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Original Artwork (Box-folder 1:4)
- Non-Fiction, n.d.
  - "Windows Into the Past" (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Historical (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Religious (Box-folder 1:7)
- Fiction, 2003-2003, n.d.
  - "Corky" (Box-folder 1:8)
  - "The Reluctant Heart"
    - Notes (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Draft A (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Draft B, 2002 (Box-folder 1:11)
    - Correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Short Stories
    - "The Risk Taker" (Box-folder 1:13)
    - "The Time of Your Life" (Box-folder 1:14)
    - Other (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Works in Progress
    - Notes on 1820s novel (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Notes on "A New Song" (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Notes on untitled novel (Box-folder 1:18)
    - Resource material (Box-folder 1:19)
    - Ideas for Writing (Box-folder 1:20)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box-folder 1:21)
- Poetry, 1986-1998, n.d.
  - Notes (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Handwritten (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Typed
- Miscellany, 1936-2003 (Box-folder 2:4)